this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program hello listeners
Marcos here I just wanted to tell you
about two things before we actually get
started with today's content first
yesterday we published an interesting
episode on Omega tau you know my my
other podcast that deals with non
software topics this time it actually
deals almost with a software topic we
talk about simulation numerical
simulation in cosmology obviously the
episode is mostly about the cosmology in
the physics but we talked quite a bit
about the computing hardware and the
software so you might want to check out
Omega tau at Omega tau podcast dotnet
the other thing I wanted to talk to you
about is our new team member Robert
bloomin he already did an episode
recently and we completely forgot to
introduce him
so that's what we'll do now hi Robert
hello Marcus welcome to the team thank
you very much it's great to be here so
where do you live what do you do I live
in San Francisco United States I've been
active in professional software
development for over 20 years I'm an
independent enterprise software
consultant focusing on financial
services currently I'm working with a
start-up that's doing something
interesting in the area of decision
science and risk management so then do
you have any special focus for your su
radio episodes for my interviews I plan
to focus on web application development
mostly on server technologies things
like emerging databases large system
issues and frameworks okay great so I
guess the listeners and of course also
the
rest of the team and myself we were
looking forward to many great episodes
about some of these topics thank you
very much it's great to be part of the
team well thanks for joining okay so
that's it with my announcements let's
get back today's content and this is
actually an episode from Robert about LP
have fun this is Robert bloomin I'm here
at Q con San Francisco 2009 with Romney
Vossler Dodd Romney vos is one of
leading thinkers and writers in the AOP
and aspectj field today we'll be
discussing his book aspectj in action
2nd edition
enterprise AOP with spring applications
romney vos welcome to software
engineering radio yeah thanks Robert
nice to be here
it's great to have you tell the
listeners about your background I what
cat SpringSource which is recently
acquired by VMware I work on various
project later aspect-oriented
programming
I'm also Spring Framework emitter mainly
work in the area of aspect-oriented
programming um so at spring source I
essentially have two roles one is to
really work with several internal
products as well as contribute to the
Spring Framework and also help customers
be successful with all of the spring and
related technologies you're one of the
first people to write about aspectj
you've been involved with it for a while
how did you get involved with aspectj
pretty much by accident anyway so at
some point I I keep recalling you know
how what was my first interaction with
aspectj
and I do remember just somehow going to
the page about a spec chain that time
into a spec he was point three version
or some very very low version and I
looked at it as like ah that's something
interesting but I kind of was this
probably was nagging me and it seemed
like wow that's the right way to do it
and at that point I kind of like said
okay interesting I kept in my mind at
some time when to look at it I really
didn't do much with it at that point
and then I started to look at about
point eight version of a spec chain and
this was maybe around 2000 and I started
to look at it and like and I started to
use it initially only in development
aspects so I wouldn't put it in
production but I would use it to improve
my productivity find out the some of the
hard bugs trade safety related ones and
then when point version 1.2 became I
started actually being very serious with
production usage wrote a bunch of
articles for Java world and then I wrote
the first edition of aspect in action
which really kind of was really almost
like a reaction to a typical claim of
about a spec G that's you can use a spec
ship for logging and tracing and that's
about it and I knew that is not right
that is not true but rather than just
making a counterpoint I just made a
counterpoint with writing a 500 pages
book and ever since I've been using
aspect in various things you know
with spring an on spring application so
it just it's been pretty associated for
a very long time with the European
aspect so softer engineering radio has
already done some episodes on AOP I
think the listeners are familiar with it
but I'd like to do a brief thumbnail of
what is AOP then we'll proceed and talk
about your book can you give us a short
description what is a opie so there are
certain class of functionality where
object-oriented programming simply
cannot do the right job for example
transaction management security log in
tracing exception handling so what we
need is actually a method or a term or
functionality or programming style that
can help us isolate these kind of
concerns or unknown as a cross-cutting
concerns from your mainline business
logic so the idea is then you can focus
on one thing at a time
it is typically said that a typical
human cannot handle more than seven
concerns at a time seven independent
concerns at a time now as far as I'm
concerned it's more like a two or three
I don't think I can handle more than two
or three concerns at a time and that's
kind of good because I mean that's
really the reality I mean human this is
this is just the way it is so what do we
need is we need a way to separate them
out so that I can focus on transaction
management once then I can go and focus
on my business logic then I can move to
security and so on so basically aspect
oriented programming is a way to really
help you realise this possibility aspect
oriented programming is a programming
language technology that enables you to
modular eyes concerns concerns and that
are known as cross-cutting concerns
because object-oriented programming is
already good at certain kind of other
concerns it just the cross-cutting
concerns where it doesn't have adequate
answer okay so there are some
terminology that we'll be using and like
you to define for the listeners point
cut yeah so when we want to implement
let's say transaction management we want
to figure out to power two things one is
where do I want to apply my transaction
where do I begin with like end that's
one part of it and the second part is
where do i what do I mean by transaction
management when I say transaction start
what code do I want to run so the first
part that is of selecting what point you
want to apply your transactions is done
through the constic well point cut you
can think of point gate like a sequel
over your program space so you can say
okay
in sequel what you say you say here are
tables give me let's say accounts where
the balance is greater than 25
whereas Poincare says things like give
me methods where the type is account and
the method starts with set or throw
certain kind of exception so essentially
you're doing a query or you program
space and you can use this point cut and
then apply your cross-cutting logic the
next term is advice advice is that
cross-cutting logic so you basically can
say before the method that I selected
using this pointer transaction
management point cut applies start your
transaction after you are done with that
method depending on whether the
exception was thrown or not you either
commit or rollback so the advice is
essentially the code that will run in
addition to or instead of the original
logic okay so an aspect combines a point
cut with some advice is that all right
exactly it also has some additional
constructs but basically advice and
point cut are the two main constituent
often ask and talk a little bit about
weaving so now once you express this
aspect and I will continue with the same
example of transaction management so you
wrote a point cut that says these are
the matter that needs to be applied with
transaction management and this is the
transaction management logic now you
need to basically have your classes and
aspects combined in such a way that you
get the end effect that you would expect
that transaction to recall certain
methods points and set certain points so
this mechanism by which you apply your
aspects to your code it's called weaving
so you've given us a brief introduction
to AOP and aspectj is obviously some
kind of Java
tool for programming AOP tells what is
aspect a so aspect js you can imagine
aspectj to be extension to Java just
like C++ was extension to C so what's
C++ did to C was added some new keywords
added some semantics and added and also
provided a compiler that could
understand those syntax aspect JIT does
exactly the same thing which our
it adds new keywords and that's
associates new semantics and it gives
you a compiler like entity which is also
sometimes called Weaver which really
understand that syntax and then produces
your byte code that byte code you can
write on any standard VM so as
allows user to define point cuts advice
and weave them together in a Java
environment exactly it also provides
your tools
mainly a gdt aspectj development tool
which is really extension to JDT which
is in Eclipse so what it allows you to
do it allows you to visualize what your
point cut is selecting what's your
effect of your advice in a comfort of
your IDE so that gives a very seamless
experience very Java like experience but
extends it to aspect oriented concepts
so aspectj provides two different
programming models the one you've been
describing is the language extension
model with the new keywords there's also
an annotation based model how does that
work so this is a new trend in last
since July came about is you you can use
annotation to how associate some
additional meaning to your programming
elements and for example you can say
this method is transactional are
transfusing by a transaction annotation
what aspect it does is it associates
some annotations to methods classes so
for example instead of using a keyword
use annotation advantage of this style
is this code is really plain Java from
Java compilers perspective so you can
just use Java compiler and compile your
aspects and you can postpone the use of
we were a bit later and we'll talk about
those as we kind of go to the interview
process so what it allow you to do it
more importantly is it allowed you to be
even more comfortable with that this is
more even closer to Java and it also
allowed you to use it from within spring
AOP environment which does not use a
bytecode viewer but uses a proxy based
mechanism so it sort of made adopting
aspects even simpler will be correct
that if you go the annotation based
model some of the some types of syntax
errors that would be detected in the
language model will not be found until a
later stage in test cycle to some extent
that is true it really depends on your
tool environment so if you use for
example Htet Htet will flag you
programming error because it does
understand Honor annotations and their
semantics meaning so it will flag those
errors but if you use some other tools
then yes it will be postponed
until the time when rubber meets the
road or so to see like when aspects is
about to be born into Java classes all
aspect is loaded and interpreted at that
time it might come with back with an
error what are the tools that aspectj
offers a programmer for defining a point
cuts that's so point cut is a language
it's very similar to the way to approach
point it is like a sequin
so essentially you write your point cut
just the way you would write a sequel so
essentially tools almost harm rather
than her so a spectator remains pretty
much take hands-off approach there so
you write point cut and it offers you
cross-cutting references view which
would allow you to understand the
interaction between your Java code and
aspect and based on that information you
can define your point cut to match your
expectations okay I think I think I
asked the wrong question so I'm gonna
ask this question again what types of
programming constructs can the
programmer pick out using the point cut
model that's a very good question
when you select when you select
programming elements you really want to
use the characteristics associated with
the programming elements so mix the most
most simple is just a method name or the
type name so you can say I want to
select all methods in account I or you
can say I want to select all matters in
account type that returns certain type
of value you can also select I want to
select all methods in account subtype
very interestingly Java 5 that also
offered us the rotation based way to
express aspect also offers an
interesting way to select wine cut join
points by the way I didn't explain the
join point concept the things that point
cut selects are known as join points
there's a bit more to it but roughly
speaking essentially it's the entities
that gets it so point cut is defining a
specification of what you want and then
the join point is like the result said
in a sequel query pretty much pretty
close only difference is join points are
considered dynamic so they occur during
execution of the system but they have
some static static what the what we call
shadow as in we know the certain method
will be selected but the join point will
come about during execution it gets best
used to it this terminology but it
eventually you will get it usually most
people carry it in a what half a day so
going back to the concept of selection
mechanism Java fires annotations and
point cut can use those annotations
let's say suppose you want to select
transactional methods it's very
difficult to come with a naming
convention or a type conversion type
naming to collect all the points all the
points that should be applied with
transaction management logic so instead
what you do is you ask Java classes to
really have those methods be inundated
with let's say a transactional
annotation or the class itself be
applied with a transactional annotation
and poink it can say all methods that
carry this annotation all all methods in
a type that carry this annotation so
essentially now you have little bit
collaboration from classes an aspect can
use that collaboration if I was writing
a purely technical aspect like a logger
I might be able to specify where I want
it to apply based on being in certain
packages certain classes but you're
talking about transaction it's really a
business concept in house the point got
going to be able to pick that out unless
you give it a little help exactly and
that's really kind of was a sore point I
mean one of the reason most people we're
finding aspect it difficult is really
the art involved in a spec J or a hope
in general it's really defining that
point cut and as you mentioned for
logging tracing exception handling you
can just simply go with a very simple
package structure or type naming
convention and you would do a reasonably
good job after you become familiar with
this tool on you're using it in a
project you start designing your project
for ease of applying point cuts to some
extent yes so some aspects if you know
that you are going to use aspects you
would not worry about those
cross-cutting concerns right away so
instead you would think how do I
indicate that I want this code to be
secure how do I indicate that I want
this code to be audited or how do I want
this code to be transaction management
and then aspects will simply leverage it
so essentially the way to look at this
annotation in this context is
annotations or kind of interfaces at
different kind of interfaces so your
mainline business interfaces for other
classes to use but the annotation based
interface is for your aspects to use so
the way in fact are the way like to
describe in a very general sense is it's
like a now you are have
multi-dimensional interfaces when you're
writing aspect the aspectj package is
exposed some reflection api's that you
can use what are the kind of things you
can access from the reflection API so
when you eat joint advice at that one
you want to know
about the joint point you are currently
working with so you want to know for
example what type what is the type in
which that method is defined or what is
the method name or what are the
arguments to the method all that
information you can get through the
reflection capability so essentially it
gives you a few access to a few
variables just like this variable there
is something on this joint point this
joint point static part and so on and
those variables then you can in go
inside that those video you can access
their properties and get refined so when
you go inside that can you then find the
data is defined by the java.lang reflect
API you can get that as well so you can
get for example the material object but
more typical usage is to really know
about the object at which the metal is
being invoked or the arguments to the
method or the method name because then
for example then you can do tracing or
you can do auditing or for let's say
transaction management you can get the
annotation itself so you can say is it a
read-only annotation what kind of
propagation and so on so suppose you
have multiple aspects that might apply
you could have a transaction on some
methods and you may be logging and
tracing more everywhere so you have
multiple aspects that all hit the same
join point is there a precedence logic
to the way that they fire absolutely so
if you don't provide any special
mechanism and it's a special castra
aspect is going to apply in some
arbitrary fashion but if you do want
let's say transaction to occur before
security then you declare your
transaction management aspect or have
higher precedence there is a construct
for that than security and then
transaction management code will have
high precedence so the before advise
will go before the security and after
advise will go after the security so
it's a pretty neat mechanism so you can
pretty much control you can pretty much
control and it just it's it's pretty
powerful mechanism you can have partial
ordering so somewhere you may say
transaction management aspect has higher
precedence than security but somebody
else you may say logging has higher
precedence than security and then it
will do the ordering between considering
all the statements aspectj provides the
ability to modify the static structure
of your type system tell us about that
and and why is that considered part of
AOP that's a good question so what let
me explain what that mechanism is so
this mechanism in
generally called intro type declaration
so one type in this case aspect is
declaring some structure for other type
and that structure could be a base class
could be introduced member so I can
introduce new methods into a type now
why is it in AOP so taking a step back
this mechanism is actually available in
other languages and essentially under
the open classes principle so you have a
class and you can open that class and
make some additional modifications and
that's pretty rich mechanism and that's
powerful at lot of in lot of ways so why
is it part of a opie however aspects
often need classes to really carry some
additional structure so for example
let's see if I have a dirty tracking
object dirty attracting aspect I want to
declare an object to be dirty or reset
it and dirtiness so I don't expect the
class itself the original class let's
say account class to carry a dirty
boolean instead I will have an aspect
dirty checking aspect to introduce that
field and then advice is going to modify
that field as needed so essentially it
gives some additional data for this it's
a way of creating per instant State for
an aspect exactly so that aspect and
then collaborators aspect can make the
object richer and use that richness so I
don't have to decide when I'm writing
this or that object that I want this
object to support being lockable or
cashable or whatever that might require
some additional state you add that in a
separate modularized concern and that's
why it's your calling and analysis let's
talk about the weaving model aspectj has
three different weaving models can you
tell us what they are so we talked about
you write aspects you write classes and
then weaving is going to take those
together and produce essentially a
system that you can deploy it into any
VM now consider situation where what if
you don't have access to source code
what aspect it does to kind of get
around all this situation is it offers
three kinds of models when it's called
source code Morse code beeping and
source code weaving takes your aspects
and classes in source code form and then
produces binary so essentially it's very
similar to what you will have every Java
compiler the second possibility is build
time binary weaving so in binary weaving
you take your aspects and
our classes in binary form so you may
have some third-party aspects library or
a third party class library and you can
combine these jar files or class files
to produce another set of jar files or
class Mac's woven Jenna file the third
possibility is I want to postpone
leaving until it is needed which would
be when I'm about to run my out run my
application so it offers a load time
viewing so what it does is it uses Java
agent so JVM TI agent and that agent
essentially detects a class being loaded
and when class gets loaded it applies
aspects at that time and then passes the
woven class file to the VM so
essentially now you can keep your build
environment intact in terms of it
doesn't is not familiar with it is not
doesn't pay attention to its being
aspect oriented and the viewer comes
only during deployment so you might
choose to use a source weaving if you
had all control of all the source the
build time weaving if you had some jar
files where you didn't have the source
and then the load time weaving I'm less
clear what's the highest and best use of
that so the source guy source time we
leaving he will use under two
circumstances one is you have control
over source for either classes and or
aspects um binary viewing is if you have
and you can mix and match these things
so he can have source and binary living
combined you can have some third party
like aspects some of your own aspects
some third party char some of your own
sources load time living is really
interesting if for example you want to
monitor let's say performance of your
application at that time you just want
to don't want to change your field
system that's what it is you know if it
is producing a war so be it and you just
deploy your war and you just want to
modify some part of your application
server or a launch script that says just
leave these performance monitoring
aspects and once you do that you will
get let's say some performance metric in
fact we have been working on a product
called spring insight which gives you
rich information about running
application and we use no time feeling
there so what we do is we expect users
to reproduce their war as they always
have been note special change you just
deployed in this special container if
you wish
Tomcat with small modifications and it's
going to apply those aspects produce
data and that data you can view it into
dashboard so because of because of who's
developing the code and how it gets
applied it may make sense to have the
weaving process be as separate as
possible from the development right and
obviously there are downsides I mean
essentially there are all of this having
the positive positives and negatives and
you have to kind of look at your
situation so for example if you want to
use load time V word then well you are
going to take the thieving hit the
performance penalty at load time so as
the classes have been loaded there will
be extra logic being run that will take
look at your class files look at your
aspects weave them together and so on so
if you are okay with that performance
penalty then load time reviewing may be
appealing because you are getting some
additional benefit as in no modification
to build time and you can take out these
aspects anytime so it's really a there
is a whole lot of discussion that goes
around this is you kind of need to
understand the system and good news is
you can mix and match so you can take
bit of performance a priority but then
you can offload it using binary being or
sauce time leaving so what are the most
obvious use cases for aspectj the way I
guess this is a question I can approach
it from the angle of essentially
adoption curve if you will so for
example if you starting with aspectj
and you are kind of wondering what is it
and you know you kind of have some
understanding of what this is but not
quite sure and you want to give it give
it a try the first kind of aspects you
will be like logging in tracing
exception handling and you can actually
get a pretty nifty data by writing an
aspect which could be like about maybe
20 lines long and that time you can even
apply load time weaving so that you
don't really want to modify your build
time so essentially make some
modification to your deployment and also
in a certain environment is literally
like couple of lines of changes and you
can start to get a feel for what aspects
you can do for you and that's exactly
the approach we are taking with spring
inside then there are other class of
aspects which what I call like a policy
enforcement aspects so their idea is you
have some policies in every project for
example you may want to say well I got
these layerings so I have my web layer
my service layer my data access layer
and there is there are some contracts my
way blur I don't want my web lair to go
directly access JDBC I want my way blade
to go to the service layer and but who
is going to enforce this contract you
can examine code periodically but that
sort of gets boring and you're never
sure you can define aspects that can
enforce this contract there are other
enough very interesting enforcement
aspects related to thread safety so for
example you may declare okay this class
is thread unsafe or how do you know that
it's being used with that understanding
as in no two threads are visiting this
object at the same time you can read
aspects that can monitor this kind of
thing in fact the very first serious
aspect I used was exactly this class so
I was working on a swing project and
those who are aware with spring there's
a very simple thread safety rule which
basically says don't use it from
multiple threads and it's a good reason
for it and it's a good rule and it's not
just swing there are other libraries
that apply have the same rule and we
were getting some this nestea problem
and this nasty problem would come once
in a while and we would give a demo to
customer and it would definitely crash
there and I go back to my desktop and
I'm trying it and it never comes up so
what I did is I wrote I kind of suspect
that this is thread safety because
that's usually characteristics like you
never know when the problem is going to
come and you if you put a debugger then
the whole characteristics dynamics
change and you didn't never see the
problem say wrote an aspect that was
just monitoring am i violating a rule am
i calling a swing component from any
thread other than the AWD thread and as
soon as that happened I log Foucault who
is caller what is the contact I could
really in a couple of days of normal
development detect all the issues and
fix those so getting back to the policy
enforcement this seems to me irrelevant
because the way of communicating those
things now is the tech lead or the
architect will maybe put some best
practices up on the wiki and you hope
everyone reads it and remembers to do it
but this allows you to have a automation
of these absolutely I mean and that's it
I would say that you know there are
there are tools like fine bars and PMD
you absolutely should use it I use them
all the time thing is those tools and
some parts of in aspectj they really
rely on static structure and that's okay
but there are dynamic things like thread
safety violation those are very
difficult to detect with static analysis
tool so you can actually
aspect you extend we want those kind of
things we'll say you have some very
interesting design patterns for using
aspects in your book but people are
gonna have to read the book to find out
often because we don't have time to go
through each and every one so there are
a bunch of other aspects we'll come back
to those later but for now let's go into
spring AOP SC Radio has done a couple of
shows on spring so we're gonna assume
people can go back in the archives and
listen to those give us briefly a
thumbnail of what dependency injection
is and then we'll talk about how that
applies to AOP so dependency injection
is another very simple idea but with
profound impact
so essentially what it says is you want
the responsibility of creating object
graph in terms of how what objects are
how objects are wired up to some
external mechanism so in this case a
container spring container for example
and that allows you to essentially have
flexibility terms of what gets wired up
with each other watch one important
thing you get out of is very simple
structure second you get very testable
code so you can for example instead of
injecting a real repository you can
inject a mock culture and that way you
can unit test your service layer what a
opie allows you to do is it augments
dependency injection to really make sure
that you don't even have to your normal
plain old java object code okay so how
do you dependency injection an AOP
interact in spring the dependency
injection takes care of keeping Java
objects simple so what we call plain old
Java objects so essentially they won't
worry about creating that's a service
object will not worry about creating a
repository so it offers simplicity from
that point of view however why
dependency injection itself is not going
to take care of things like transaction
management and security and exception
handling and so on that's where AOP
steps in so he hopi says alright you
keep your plain old java objects keep
them plain but will apply these
cross-cutting concerns through aspects
and therefore as a result dependency
injection along with AOP and along with
hurting enterprise a service abstraction
keep your core very clean
how does a developer create an aspect in
spring when spring started spring
couldn't really use aspectj
because of the bytecode beaming model
and it wasn't well accepted that you
can use anything other than Java to
develop your systems um so spring
created its own mechanism using proxy
based a framework and that time it also
had its own programming model but since
spring to dot o that programming model
is changed now you can use the
annotation style aspect that I mentioned
earlier with spring so what you do is
you write your class a class and audit
it with annotations such as an aspect
and point guard and before etc and those
aspects you instantiate a bean
corresponding to those aspect and those
aspects will spring will then take care
of a plot creating proxies for the other
beans and making those proxies call this
aspect code appropriately so your aspect
is a bean in the spring container and
you could for example dependency inject
other beans in your container into the
aspect absolutely so they are
first-class beans so they you can do
whatever you can do with other beans you
can do with aspects as well
so that is a bit more powerful
programming model than purely aspectj
where you couldn't necessarily inject
other pieces of code into an aspect or
easily with spring AOP in fact with
spring container you can actually do
that so you can have your aspects woman
using aspect chief byte code weaving
instruction at a spring bean so all you
have to do is basically define like a
normal being accept user attribute
factory method and aspectj has a each
aspect carries a factory method called
aspect of that you use and that will
instantiate a bean and once that mean is
instantiated you can use normal
dependency injection Meccans you can
instantiate an aspect j aspect as a
spring bean with in spring contain
exactly and that's actually a good
pattern one of the good patterns is
dependency mechanism is good no matter
whether you use normal puja plain old
java objects or aspects so you should
use aspects with dependency injection so
that your aspect is more testable spring
also enables you to
dependency inject into objects that are
not created by the container how does
that work so normally depends injection
mechanism is restricted to you declare a
bean and then you declare its properties
and those properties are typically
references to other beans or scalars
that's roughly the dependency injection
mechanism
now you may have a situation where you
have objects such as account and
customer now you are not going to have
beans for spring beans for those objects
because each one is unique so you can't
you can't configure it exactly so
essentially dependent for dependency
injection to work you need to have
container in charge of creation whereas
with account and customer kind of object
domain objects in general you you are
probably creating through some Orem
framework and that's creating those
objects so what we have done is in
spring is we created a set of aspects
and those are reasonable aspects you can
use them without writing an aspect so
all you do is you mark your objects your
classes with at configurable annotation
there are other mechanisms too but more
popular ways to just mark your classes
with that configurable and aspect jeeves
into this classes to say whenever object
is constructed or deserialized
it will inject it with dependencies so
under the hood it's got some kind of
point cuts that allow it to trap the
events where the injection needs exactor
so there were this is leading is to a
point you made in your book you suggest
that the decomposition that is very
popular in these type of applications
into services and entities is really a
technical artifact that doesn't
necessarily make sense now that you have
these other these capabilities what did
you have a that's very good question and
I try to make this point in various ways
so what is typical web application
looking at your web layer then that web
layer called service layer service let's
called repository layer repository calls
database like ORM or JDBC and that's
nice and neat you know it seems
reasonable architecture the problem kind
of is you kind of look back and saying
what is this service layer exactly doing
in most cases you will find that service
layer is a mere forwarding mechanism to
repository or to domain objects or and
then you look at domain objects and you
see like well really anemic as in they
just have getters and setters and really
have no interesting behavior so now you
start to look at and saying well then
why do you need service services because
we can configure the service for
dependency injection but we can't
configure the and that's part of the
reason and other mechanisms other reason
is once you have services as beans
can apply spring AOP because then you
can create proxies for its so sling is
in charge of creating synthesis so it
can then create a proxy to it so we're
gonna come back to the proxies go ahead
on this question and then we'll talk
about proxies and next so you should not
create anything in software that doesn't
have a need doesn't have a real need
that's the basic principle I'm going to
go with so you have to look back and
saying - I really need services if if I
give you a mechanism that says you can
apply transaction wherever else you want
it doesn't need to be spring bean and
you can inject dependency injection
wherever you want you don't need it
doesn't need to be spring bean if I give
you that what do you really want service
layer also it turns out to be is
actually no you don't need service layer
for just this simple purpose I will
expand on there are places where you
need service layer I will come back to
that in a minute so I think your point
so far is the service and entity
combined constitute a single abstraction
from a domain modeling standpoint and we
just split them up into two halves
because of really technically exactly so
I I want to look at it like saying is it
a technical reason or there is a real
domain or application level reason for
it
so what you can do is since aspectj
provides a mechanism that can extend
transaction management security etc to
any object and it can extend mechanism
of configurability as in dependency
injection to any object what else you
need in fact Spring has open source
project call spring rule it takes these
ideas and actually creates a product out
of it
so I'm gonna come back to spring Roo so
let's let's come back to that so you
will see that once you start to use
aspectj in real good reasonable sense
reason for using service layer from this
simplistic perspective at least goes
away now I will go back to service layer
you need service layers in many cases
and those service layer is typically as
a facade to your application so let's
say you want to expose some
functionality of your application to
let's outside outside pavement system
right so essentially integration layer
that service layer comes because it
makes sense from your application point
of view to serve other parts of your big
system that case I would say quired you
service so essentially don't use service
because somehow technical reasons are
driving it
you seriously if it is naturally that
you find a natural reason to have us I
guess it's interesting to realize how
much of design patterns come about by
convention and then you forget why the
convention applied in the first place
till some new technology comes along and
forces you to rethink how you actually
wonderful I mean I think it we are at in
Java world we are at a crossroads where
some of the assumption that we made like
we must do certain ways is being shaken
not just aspectj but other languages too
that's really a interesting position
there's a perception among programmers
it aspect-oriented programming is
something to help you with these
technical aspects that cross cut your
entire code base but I'm wondering
should we also be thinking about our
domain design and our domain model in
terms of hierarchy which is object
orientation and then cross-cutting
domain concerns which is aspect
orientation and should aspect oriented
design become one of the tools in our
design tool absolutely I mean look at
classes is classes often serve different
clients and what my client I mean
different other classes and each of
those clients typically tend to have
different perspective so for example if
you have a domain class there are some
parts that are really meant for
consumption of GPA some ORM framework
some parts are there meant for debugging
and
to string and other others other methods
so if you use aspect-oriented
programming you can segregate that so
you can say here is a domain core domain
logic
maybe then there are some additional
domain logic that come from only some
perspective so for example an ordering
system should it care about inventory
management maybe maybe not let your
business decide that but if it does
should you make order take care of
inventory management right inside its
code probably not how about segregating
into a part and that part can sort of
for example take care of those inventory
management or an interesting example is
a human API interfaces so Martin Fowler
blogged about this at floors back so the
idea is what is the right interface to a
to an to a class one in one one class of
thinking is minimalist so offer the
minimal interface that anybody can build
on the top of that interface but other
one says well if I use minimalist
interface then that means I have to
write a lot of code myself why does
it'd offer me a typical interface that I
can just use it in a simplistic fashion
so you can use aspect G to introduce
that minimal interface and then you can
kind of bridge gap between these two
groups of thinking so bike or the object
offers the minimal interface and aspect
introduced the humanization api so there
are several ways you can look at this
class and saying class doesn't need to
be written in one place so I guess maybe
the core message there is a class
doesn't need to be written in one place
it can be segregated into variety of
ways and those can compose a final view
of the class this one is actually very
deep question it's really difficult to
address it you know so you'd mentioned
this proxy based aspects tell us what
that is so you want to let's say apply
aspect to an object there to mechanism
one modify the class file as in bytecode
as seen by the VM and put additional
code in that byte core that's one
mechanism other mechanism is take the
class object as it is and wrap it in
some other object and that object is
proxy essentially you make sure that the
proxy gives the same API to the outside
world so if it is account service if
your class if your beam is implementing
account service let proxy also implement
account service to the outside world it
looks like an account service however
when somebody makes a call on proxy
before you forward it to the underlying
object you can do some additional stuff
and on the way out as well and that's
how you can implement your before advice
after the proxy wrapper is spring's way
of accomplishing the weaving in spring
AOP exactly without using a special
compiler auto-reverse
you've mentioned the spring route
project which relies heavily on aspect a
what is spring Roo spring Roo is a
project that brings productivity that
you see in rails and Grails environment
in a statically typed language which is
Java so what spring does is it combines
Java with aspectj
with some code generation and gives you
a very good productivity so you can
create a good web application in a
matter of few minutes and how does it
use aspectj to make them possible
several ways so difficult problem when
you say code generation is usually you
tend to shy away from such tools because
when you use code generation you would
typically see the code get generated and
marked with a block do not edit it and
if you edit it bad things will happen
and that tends to really kind of you
know
you are so what spring does is it
generates code in aspects that are
associated with the main class so in the
main class you simply write your domain
logic so you write your fields you write
your methods business logic you do what
you would do in a typical plain old java
object and you will take that class and
generate associated aspects and those
aspects introduce methods to your domain
objects so it will introduce let's say a
finder method or introduce a two string
method it will introduce all those
methods it will attach annotations at
the appropriate places and you don't
have to worry about it you don't modify
the aspects if you want to override the
behavior in an aspect you simply write
that method in the main class and then
the aspect code won't disturb that code
so essentially the code generated is
kept away from your main classes that's
one way the second is it uses
transaction management woven using a
switching so it is just springg aspectj
the aspects that are written as a part
of Spring Framework to do that it also
uses the dependency injection into your
domain objects so essentially with Roo
what rural iäôs you to do is it allows
you to focus on what is really important
that is your domain class so you worry
about your class and everything else
kind of comes through that and that's
all in my opinion how software should be
written you should focus on what is
really important when you read the
typical class that's been hand coded you
have this tangling of all the domain
concerns and all the technical concerns
in the class and this in really allows
you to untangle and have each thing you
understood on its own absolutely and
when we talked about earlier service
layer and how does it or repositories
layer and unnecessary layering Roo
allows you to really get rid of all
those things so Roo class it can
introduce repository like behavior
service itself you just introduce
behavior in the class itself so you have
very rich domain model and that Roo
handle everything else so it's really
kind of being productivity and it's kind
of very interesting when you watch Roo
presentation that from scratch you can
create a full-fledged application that
you can test it along with the test it
writes tests as well everything done in
matter of let's say half an hour spring
is very popular in developing enterprise
applications what are some of the more
common enterprise cross-cutting concerns
the invention transactions certainly
that's a bit yeah so we talked about a
earlier policy enforcement and tracing
the other one starts at like auditing so
if you got some marketing requirements
saying some sort of compliance HIPPA
compliance may be there you want to
monitor your application at various
points it's an extension of tracing
voided into from a different very
different perspective it's more from a
business from a business perspective so
you have requirements so what you can do
is now you can annotate what are the
classes what are methods so we need to
keep track of whoever has done any
transactions on the account so that you
know in case something really goes wrong
it may save your company so from that
point of view those are the aspects you
start at the like like a simple aspect
which is extension of tracing but more
you must put in production they are not
something that you put in one day and
take it out like tracing aspect part of
the front the part of the business
requirements of your application exactly
and then you have concurrency control
those are also enterprise application so
now with all of the Ajax and other
things going on
you can have your objects in session for
example being bombarded with queries
from multiple threads and you have to
make sure that they behave the way you
wanted so essentially if you are in a
concurrent environment you want to make
sure that your concurrency is taken care
of or whatever policies that you may
have set up appropriately fall order
then of course the transaction
management it's deep most and the first
aspect that you are likely to use if you
are let's say creating a spring based
application spring provides you is some
pre-built transaction management aspects
correct yes and that's an interesting
one is where you may actually be using
AOP and not realize it because the way
it is it's really encapsulated in a very
nice way where it really all boils down
to writing a couple of lines of code in
your configuration file yes you could
say the EOP is a generalization of a
capability that the j2ee servers had a
declarative transaction management
that's a really good to put it I mean
essentially in fact I just when I was
working on second edition of book and
when I was about to write my preface I
went back and my frustration and say
what did I say then back then and I kind
of was pleasantly surprised I mean I
probably was overboard and I made a
prediction that didn't come out as
quickly as I thought but I essentially
said like you know what do you need a
j2u service server for you need first of
all a web server what kind of set
kind of manager and then he needed
somebody to take care of your security
and transaction management rather than
by taking this whole thing solution has
a one thing monolithic solution can you
not pick and choose and say oh here is
the security I want here's the
transaction management I want because
then I don't have to like surrender to
like how the way server does AJ to a
server does I can say you know what I
want a field level security so I'm going
to take this additional aspects so you
can essentially create your own
modularity gives you plug ability so
within a spring project you have a spec
J as you explain you can use a spec J to
create aspects you can use spring opie
spring AOP what do you think how should
we approach trying to use these should
we use one and pick the one we like
should people use the best tool for the
job and mix and match them together or
what's the best use of one versus the
other
that's actually a very interesting
question especially if you're just
starting with a o P and you kind of want
to say I mean one other thing is that
that happened with aspectj let's say
what last four years or so is we know
how lot more choices back in the days it
was very simple there was one kind of
viewing well there are two kinds of
living and that's about it there was one
kind of syntax and that's about it
now you kind of have lots of choices and
choices while good and also clear
confusion right you know what do I do
I mean do I use this kind of syntax or
other kind of syntax do I use one kind
of living or other the way I kind of
approach is is if you are starting with
this let's say you are already a spring
application I would say start with
spring AOP
right aspects using that annotation base
syntax call at a spec sheet syntax use
that syntax to read your aspects leave
them using Springs o'clock see based AOP
and start understanding what F is all
about start understanding how to write a
pointer start understanding how to write
an advice at some point you will kind of
exhaust the possibilities because spring
AOP applies a couple of couple of
limitations there it applies only to
spring beans and it can only intercept
methods so if you want to let's say say
I want to advise custard or or I want to
apply an exception
block you can't do that with spring AOP
so when you reach that point you go to a
spec check because now you already learn
the concepts you already know how to
write an aspect now you're only learning
how to weave them using a different
mechanism and once you understand that
you can you
also exhaust so at some point although
probably it will take you very very far
where you might want to use even more
complex and powerful techniques and
those techniques are also available only
with traditional syntax so at that point
you can switch over to that traditional
syntax only for some aspects so
therefore it's more mix-and-match so in
my experience I started out using these
two tools independently I arrived at the
view that the spring AOP aspects are
larger grain and more suited for the
business concerns whereas with a spec J
you can get as fine-grained as you want
and you may be dealing with things like
threading and concurrency that aren't
really business concerns they're more
technical concerns as is that a common
view but that's that's a good way to get
started I mean it cinches the way I kind
of say is get started with spring AOP
and let experience be your best guide so
at some point you will automatically
come to your own conclusion what is
appropriate I'd like to pick your brain
a little bit about some issues around
AOP and why it maybe isn't I'm more
widely used than it is in the six years
since you came out with the first
edition of your book there are still
relatively few titles on AOP compared to
the object oriented revolution which
produced a massive explosion of books
and still has hundreds of titles is AOP
mainstream or is it still a little bit
out there considered more experimental
this point I would definitely say it's
not experimental anymore
and we can talk about some of the
products that use a opine like in a very
core way but coming back to your
question of number of number of books
being published there are actually quite
a few books that could publish right
around my book got published so until
2005 or 2006 lots of books that cut
population there was a kind of a wide in
between and then I have my book and
hopefully it gets followed with other
books one other thing is object-oriented
programming is depending on who you talk
to and depending on what you consider
start of it it's about thirty years old
so it does take actually a significant
amount of significant duration why until
people start to get comfortable with it
and III know I mean I mean I use
object-oriented when it was sort of
already mainstream but I have seen like
especially in I mean I worked in real
time with real time systems an object or
it was pretty frowned upon in that those
system so it takes quite a bit of time
to get adapted so I would say aspect
oriented programming is a sort of a
midpoint it is inflection point at which
it better start to make inroads into
some make in a core way unfortunately in
my opinion it is already making that way
and that's it's going to take a while
before it really starts to become like
something that you sort of do it without
thinking too much about it
so you say in your book that we passed
the peak of overhype and we're in the
productive plateau of the Gartner hype
hype psychology care to elaborate on
that yeah
so the Gartner hype cycle basically
follows through several phases you know
essentially it starts is a technology
trigger so product gets announced and
then sort of you know if it is something
good or something you can think as it
good then it can get hyped so everybody
starts to go on this bandwagon saying
alright aspect-oriented programming
wonderful I can use it for anything
and that's happens for every technology
and in fact we can already see like
certain things are going through that
phases right now so it goes to that very
high expectation everybody thinks every
problem can be solved with that
technology and it can't it wasn't really
meant to even so then it suddenly people
said oh well I can't really do that with
that technology and it goes down and
into like a trough of disillusionment so
you are like disillusioned saying it
really wasn't what I thought it would be
and at that time however those who
really understood the technology
reasonably well or those who are looking
at it already from a very reasonable
point of view starts to use it as a
competitive advantage they say like okay
this technology can do that but not
other things so they start to use
technology in its its sweet spot and
then it goes on to what I call like a
slope of enlightenment the slope of
enlightenment is like you really
understand the technology strengths and
weaknesses and starts to use with its
strengths but not for its weaknesses and
then it goes to plateau productivity
where you don't really think much of it
like for example Java right you don't go
and brag about using Java anymore there
was a time 10 years back when you would
say oh you are a Java programmer
wonderful you don't say that anymore
now you have to say any of these cool
new languages and then you can still
brag about them so I believe that it's a
space somewhere on the slope of
enlightenment and it will probably reach
particulate or productivity in next few
years and the reason I see it
we'll see that aspect a pop scene sort
of unexpected places so you will see
that there comes spring Roo product all
of a sudden it uses it it doesn't make a
big fuss out of it it simply says hey
look here is a product that gives you
product ability by the way it uses a
spec check or spring inside it says here
is way to get insight into your
application by the way it is a spec
sheet what would you say to people who
think that a opie is a compensation for
java being too static and not offering
meta programming features can everything
that you're calling AOP be done with
meta programming yes and no right so can
meta programming modify the classes to
add nutrients yes it can can meta
programming
modify methods to add extra beer
absolutely it can the question is there
is a possibility and is is that the way
to do it it's a programming language
innumerable possibility right I mean I
can write enterprise application in
assembly code it will drive me insane
but I can so possibility is never an
issue it's a question of correct doing
it the right way
meta programming in my opinion is very
powerful too and in some cases it's
really critical in fact that huge meta
programming and we later on we probably
hopefully will talk about spring ruin I
can talk about in that context meta
programming how it pops up there but
going back to the question is is it you
know do I should I if I have meta
programming do I still need a OB I would
say yes
ao P brings actually discipline to meta
programming the meta programming is very
powerful but you sometime one-to-one too
much power right so in fact if you think
about it even object-oriented
programming is a discipline approach
that says okay here is a procedure
programming and you can you really do
anything you want but encapsulation is
really cutting the power right it's
really I mean think about it right why
do you need a private field if you make
a public it's powerful what do you want
discipline so is it really it's really a
balance of power versus discipline so
you could think of aspectj as a dsl for
doing certain a limited subset of meta
programming functions
absolutely I just want to make it clear
that I do not want to say that meta
programming substitutes
aspectj AOP I also don't want to say
that it will be substrate meta
programming they both have their place
in in a programming system and you
should use them correctly you are going
to get a quite a bit of laboratory let's
talk a bit about the aspectj project it
is an open source project it's been
adopted into the Eclipse family
tell us the history of the aspectj
project so aspect just started at Xerox
PARC
in about 1996 and it was started the
person who led this project is Gabriel
chrysalis and interestingly to connect
back to the earlier question he wrote a
very interesting and very well referred
book on meta programming so he knows
what might have programming is and he
knows what could be powerful and that's
why he got that perspective saying what
would it take come bring meta
programming to a statically typed
language and that's basically how that
spec just started anyway suspect just
started it was open source project in um
under a different license and at some
point it got transferred to eclipse Don
are under APL slice appear license it
gives license which is very liberal and
at that time most of the people working
for aspects away from IBM and later on
agent Collier who is the especially left
IBM and joined SpringSource um just
about that time also join us spring
source I was independent consultant back
then and bit later
Andy Clement who is who was with IBM
also joined SpringSource recently and
you're Heisenberg who is a doctor else -
oh just finished his PhD and working
with EOP for a long time also joined
SpringSource and working on aspectj
so a lot of development is going on in a
spec chain and spring sources right now
support all aspects so essentially I
have pretty much the sponsor of a
Spectre project so most of the main
committers to a spec J are spring source
employees you said there's quite a lot
of development going on can you tell us
what's gonna be in some of the
subsequent releases right so just I will
take a perspective like what happened
over the last couple of years one other
thing that happened is aspect you got
the core got stabilized took a long time
for a spec you to really stabilize and
this is not really only with aspect J it
just a lot of other projects also got
bit sort of sidetracked if you will in
then at the end for good reasons if you
like genetic studies but aspect you also
got pretty sidetracked with you know
making sure that annotations are
supported well making sure that all the
new viewing models are supported well
generic self supported weight and so on
and as a result some of the issues such
as performance memory consumption got
sidetracked or last two years there has
been tremendous amount of energy that
has been put into these issues so
spec J compile-time performance has
improved significantly aspect G's memory
usage has gone down significantly
the bugs are far fewer now I mean you
really have to find a very complex case
to really find a bug so there was a time
when there were bugs but nobody was
there to look at it because they were
busy with other things like making sure
genetics a support unit now if you give
a bulk of which with anything related to
core the bugs get fixed like in a few
days matter would you say the project is
well funded and well staff now
absolutely and there are more people
that might be joining project as well
they're an active community around it
yeah so aspectj has two communities I
would say one is the core aspect G user
community and then they just bring out
the community both user mailing lists
are pretty active both forums in case of
spring AOP days of forum and aspect it
is a meaning list they're pretty active
so if you ask a good question or
question in general you're likely to get
a very helpful answer that's another
thing you will see is if we join a spec
G community you will be welcomed you
will be helped where can people go if
they want to learn more about the
project and the community yeah so go to
eclipse.org slash aspectj and go to
eclipse.org slash a JDT for the tools
project and they're a mailing list you
can join those for spring AOP go to a
spring framework and org and then you
will get into forum and there is a
spring AOP forum so those are the places
to hang around you've come out this fall
with the second edition of your book
what is new in the second edition from
the first edition so the first edition
was really about what is a OB and what
can you do with it it did not however
have a very solid context in terms of
what application of frameworks we are
going to be used so at that time spring
was very new and wasn't a mainstream
framework now spring is de facto
standard in case of java lightweight
frameworks so what I did is with the
second edition is to put aspectj
in spring context so you you you create
your application based on spring and use
aspectj to create the cross-cutting
concerns around it so what I did is and
more thing I changed one is the whole
Chavez changed a lot in last six years
there I could use JDBC and
that was a reasonable solution back then
now you have to use ORM framework
earlier I could just use an
and just a bad scripts and that was good
enough now I have to use and and maven
and other things so what I've done is I
kind of modernized every single thing so
my first edition the goal was to make it
relevant to every Java programmer the
second edition wanted to keep this goal
so Java changed and so did book I also
basically modified how aspects are
written because my knowledge of how
aspects are supposed to be used changed
by working with customers and various
projects I have much better
understanding of how you should be using
a spec chain so I kind of basically put
all this knowledge together what how
Java has changed what my perspective has
changed and put them into this book
who's the intended audience for the work
mainly I would say mid to advanced Java
programmer so if you're really
comfortable with Java then you should
look at a spec change you also if you're
a spring user then you are definitely
audience here every pretty much every
application every example is based on
spring where can people find the book go
to Manning comm slash la - or just
probably you can search inspection
action on Google if people would like to
follow your work
do you have a blog or Twitter yeah I
have a blog a blog couple of places it's
not very active but I intend to I have
series of blogs that I should be coming
up soon a one is on Spring Framework
steam blog
another one is a spec TV t.com or you
can go to Romney was dot-com slash blog
do it now if people want to follow your
work do you write regularly anywhere
yeah you can follow me first thing is on
Twitter so you can just follow me on
Twitter comment Romney was our am and I
VA s and you can follow my spring source
team blog where I blog as well
you can follow also on Romney was calm
slash blog where I put some not
necessarily related to spring some more
specific issues that blog about those at
my personal blog and if people would
like to reach you if they have any
questions about your book or comments
how can they reach you um a few places
you can ask me on if it is related to
aspectj just ask your on aspect G user
mailing list I hang out there so I might
answer there there is a books forum on
Manning's website so if you go to
Manning comm and look at my books link
there is a forum you can ask book
question related to the book itself
if you want to ask about spring AOP you
can ask come spring forum I've followed
that as well and you can always find my
email address and ask me questions we'll
put all that information in the show
notes ramna Vossler dodd thank you for
telling listeners it's software
engineering radio about your new book
and about aspectj thank you Robert this
was really nice talking to you thanks
for listening to software engineering
radio software engineer radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
se - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the se radio team
by our website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious links and the
slash dot button to contact the team
please send email to team at SC - radio
net or if you're specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your comments this episode of se radio
as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the pot size Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas on top